[
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is NOT a component of aggregate demand (AD)?",
        "choice1": "Wages",
        "choice2": "Consumption",
        "choice3": "Net Exports",
        "choice4": "Government spending",
        "choice5": "Investment",
        "answer": 1,
        "explanation": "A is correct because the formula for GDPr is C + I + G + Xn, or Consumption + Investment + Government Spending + Net Exports."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following could cause a left shift of the AD graph?",
        "choice1": "An increase in consumer confidence",
        "choice2": "An increase in interest rates",
        "choice3": "An increase in government spending",
        "choice4": "An increase in exports",
        "choice5": "An increase in consumption spending",
        "answer": 2,
        "explanation": "The answer is B. With an increase of interest rates, the price of investment would increase. Therefore the demand for investment would decrease as a result. "
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following best describes the relationship illustrated by the short-run aggregate supply (SRAS) curve?",
        "choice1": "The positive relationship between the price level and the quantity of output produced",
        "choice2": "The positive relationship between the price of a single good and the quantity supplied by producers",
        "choice3": "The fixed amount of all output that will be produced, which does not respond to the price level",
        "choice4": "The negative relationship between the price level and the quantity of output produced",
        "choice5": "The positive relationship between the unemployment rate and the amount of output supplied",
        "answer": 1,
        "explanation": "A is correct because the SRAS is an upward sloping curve. This is due to the law of supply ( with an increase of price will follow with an increase of output). "
    },
    {
        "question": "What happens to inflation and the unemployment rate as you move to the right along the short-run aggregate supply (SRAS) curve?",
        "choice1": "Inflation doesn’t change and unemployment doesn’t change.",
        "choice2": "Inflation increases and unemployment doesn’t change.",
        "choice3": "Inflation decreases and the unemployment rate doesn’t change.",
        "choice4": "Inflation decreases and the unemployment rate increases.",
        "choice5": "Inflation increases and the unemployment rate decreases.",
        "answer": 5,
        "explanation": "The answer is E. There is a tradeoff between inflation and unemployment along the SRAS curve because, as you move to the right along the curve, there is an increase in the price level and an increase in output. More output lowers the unemployment rate."
    },
    {
        "question": "The marginal propensity to consume (MPC) in Hamsterville is 0.75. What will be the size of the change in aggregate demand that will occur as a result of a 1 million dollar increase in the government spending component of AD?",
        "choice1": "$.75 million",
        "choice2": "$4 million",
        "choice3": "$.25 million",
        "choice4": "$3 million",
        "choice5": "$1.75 million",
        "answer": 2,
        "explanation": "B is correct; Spending multiplier = 1/1-MPC; 1/1-0.75 = 4"
    },
    {
        "question": "The LRAS is to the left of AD/AS curves. Which of the following best describes how the economy will adjust in the long run?",
        "choice1": "Long-run aggregate supply will increase and the price level will stay the same.",
        "choice2": "Aggregate demand will decrease and the price level will increase.",
        "choice3": "Long-run aggregate supply will decrease and the price level will not change.",
        "choice4": "Short-run aggregate supply will decrease and the price level will increase.",
        "choice5": "Aggregate demand will increase and the price level will increase.",
        "answer": 4,
        "explanation": "D is correct; there are several reasons why the short-run aggregate supply (SRAS) curve will decrease. First, when output is higher than full-employment output, the unemployment rate is lower than the natural rate of unemployment. This puts upward pressure on nominal wages which decreases SRAS. Also, this kind of output gap increases inflationary expectations, which also decreases SRAS."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following best describes aggregate supply?",
        "choice1": "The amount buyers plan to spend on output",
        "choice2": "A schedule showing the relationship between inputs and outputs",
        "choice3": "A schedule showing the trade-off between inflation and unemployment",
        "choice4": "A schedule indicating the level of real output that will be purchased at each possible price level",
        "choice5": "A schedule indicating the level of real output that will be produced at each possible price level",
        "answer": 5,
        "explanation": "There is no explanation currently!"
    },
    {
        "question": "If Maria Escalera’s disposable income increases from $600 to $650 and her level of personal consumption expenditures increase from $480 to $520, you may conclude that her marginal propensity to",
        "choice1": "consume is 0.8.",
        "choice2": "consume is 0.4.",
        "choice3": "consume is 0.25.",
        "choice4": "save is 0.8.",
        "choice5": "save is 0.25",
        "answer": 1,
        "explanation": "A is correct because MPC=dc/dy  (MPC= change in consumption/ change in disposable income) (520-480)/(650-600) MPC=0.8"
    },
    {
        "question": "A change in which of the following will cause the aggregate demand curve to shift?",
        "choice1": "Energy prices",
        "choice2": "Productivity rates",
        "choice3": "Consumer wealth",
        "choice4": "Prices of inputs",
        "choice5": "Prices of consumer goods",
        "answer": 3,
        "explanation": "The answer is C. A consumer’s income affects the consumer’s consumption. The less of a consumer's income, the less spending ability they have. "
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following will most likely result in stagflation?",
        "choice1": "Increase in aggregate demand",
        "choice2": "Increase in aggregate supply",
        "choice3": "Decrease in aggregate demand",
        "choice4": "Decrease in aggregate supply",
        "choice5": "Increase in the marginal propensity to save",
        "answer": 4,
        "explanation": "The answer is D. When aggregate supply shifts to the left, the price level increases, output falls, and unemployment rises. High prices (inflation) + high unemployment = stagflation. When you add inflation and unemployment together, you get the Misery Index."
    },
    {
        "question": "When there is a federal budget surplus:\nI. the Federal Reserve increased the money supply in a given year.\nII. the Federal Reserve decreased the money supply in a given year.\nIII. the government spent more in a year than it received in taxes.\nIV. the government collected more taxes in a year than it spent.",
        "choice1": "I",
        "choice2": "II",
        "choice3": "III",
        "choice4": "IV",
        "choice5": "None of the above.",
        "answer": 4,
        "explanation": "The answer is D. When the government collects more in taxes than it spends, the federal budget shows a surplus."
    },
    {
        "question": "Gross domestic product (GDP) in Marthland is decreasing, plunging Marthaland into a recession. How will the response of automatic stabilizers to decreasing GDP in Marthaland affect the economy of Marthaland?",
        "choice1": "The government of Marthaland will respond by implementing expansionary fiscal policy, such as a new infrastructure project.",
        "choice2": "Tax revenues will decrease without governmental action, which will keep consumption and output from falling further.",
        "choice3": "Transfer payments will decrease automatically, decreasing spending and output.",
        "choice4": "The government will respond by passing a one-time tax cut to stimulate the economy.",
        "choice5": "The government will implement contractionary fiscal policy, such as decreasing government spending.",
        "answer": 2,
        "explanation": "The answer is B. When national income decreases, so do the taxes collected from that income. A reduction in taxes leaves more income available for consumption, preventing consumption from falling further during a recession."
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements makes a correct distinction between the short run and the long run?",
        "choice1": "Short run: wages are fixed; long run: wages are fully flexible",
        "choice2": "Short run: wages are fully flexible; long run: wages are fixed",
        "choice3": "Short run: unemployment will increase in response to inflation; long run: unemployment is not affected by inflation",
        "choice4": "Short run: aggregate supply slopes downwards; long run: aggregate supply slopes upwards",
        "choice5": "Short run: less than six months has passed; long run: more than six months has passed",
        "answer": 1,
        "explanation": "The answer is A. The term 'short run' means that not enough time has passed for input prices to adjust. The term 'long run' means that enough time has passed to allow all input prices to adjust fully."
    },
    {
        "question": "What will happen to the size of the expenditure multiplier and the size of the tax multiplier when the marginal propensity to save (MPS) increases?",
        "choice1": "Both decrease",
        "choice2": "Both increase",
        "choice3": "The size of the tax multiplier increases, the size of the spending multiplier decreases",
        "choice4": "The size of the tax multiplier doesn't change, the size of the spending multiplier increases",
        "choice5": "The size of the tax multiplier increases, the size of the spending multiplier doesn't change",
        "answer": 1,
        "explanation": "The answer is A. The MPS appears in the denominator of both the tax multiplier and the expenditures multiplier, so an increase in the MPS will make both of these measures smaller. This is a phenomenon that is sometimes called the 'paradox of thrift.'"
    }
]